Finding Aid for the Society for Psychophysiological Research Records LSC.1194
UCLA Library Special Collections
Society for Psychophysiological Research records
circa 1955-1987
UCLA Library Special Collections
Society for Psychophysiological Research (U.S.)
LSC.1194
14.5 linear feet (21 boxes and 4 cartons)
The Society for Psychophysiological Research was created to foster research related to physiology and psychology. The collection consists of correspondence, minutes, programs, publications, slides, and miscellaneous printed materials related to the Society for Psychophysiological Research.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIO MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audio materials. Audio materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marion A. Wenger, 1977 & 1982.
Gift of David Shapiro, 1989.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9929769503606533
Biography
The Society for Psychophysiological Research was created to foster research related to physiology and psychology. The organization produces scientific literature and holds annual meetings for presentations and discussion of topics such as instrumentation, methodology, experimental results, and theoretical interpretations.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, minutes, programs, publications, slides, and miscellaneous printed materials related to the Society for Psychophysiological Research. Includes copies of the Polygraph Newsletter and the Psychophysiology Newsletter. Also includes oral history interviews (tapes and transcripts) with charter members of the organization.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Society for Psychophysiological Research Records (22 items).
Society for Psychophysiological Research (U.S.)--Archives.
- Audio / Visual
  - Slides. (New York City). (Detroit). (Washington D.C.). (Houston)., 1961 1963 1964 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notes describing contents of cassette tape. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Slides., 1958-1965. (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Ax, Albert F.
  - Letters from Ax--opportunities., 1961-1962. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Ax--to applicants., 1961-1963. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Ax--offering employment., 1960-1963. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Ax--seeking employment., 1961-1963. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Positions available--as of, July 12, 1963. (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Board minutes and notes., 1963-1964. (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Journal contracts., 1963-1964. (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Ads for the journal Psychophysiology., 1964. (Box 12, Folder 18)
- Davis, R.C.
  - Materials from Davis's files, sent by his son Christoper., February 7, 1977, 1959. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Edelberg, Robert
  - Letter to David Shapiro explaining the nature of the archive material., June 6, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous papers., 1965-1966. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (file incomplete)., 1965-1966. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes., 1966. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous papers., 1967. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Employment
  - Addressograph., 1965. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Application requests., 1964-1965. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - APSS membership list and by-laws., 1964-1965. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Ax, Albert F., 1963-1965. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Letters in--A., 1963-1964. (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Letters in--B., 1964-1965. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Brown, Clinton C., Ph. D., 1964-1965. (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Letters in--C., 1964-1965. (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Letters in--D., 1964-1965. (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Letters in--E., 1964. (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Edelberg, Robert--correspondence., 1964-1965. (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Letters out--F., 1965. (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Letters out--G., 1964-1965. (Box 13, Folder 18)
- Fowles, Donald
  - Programs for archives., 1966-1967, 1979-1983. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Minutes., 1978-1979. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Minutes., 1979-1980. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Minutes., 1980-1981. (Box 16, Folder 5)
- General Items
  - Membership lists., 1964. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Geographical distribution of membership. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Complete membership lists--geographical and alphabetical., 1963-1965. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Society for Psychophysiological Research by-laws., 1963-1966. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Ballots for Board of Directors., 1965. (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Graham, David T.
  - General., 1967. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - General., 1967-1968. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Nominees., 1969-1971. (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Society for Psychophysiological Research., 1970. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - 1971 meeting., 1970. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - 1972 meeting., 1970. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - General., 1969-1970. (Box 21, Folder 9-10)
  - 1970 meeting., 1969-1970. (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Exhibitors., 1969-1970. (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - General., 1969. (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - General., 1971. (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - General., 1965. (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Board meeting., 1970. (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Psychophysiology (journal)., 1970-1971. (Box 21, Folder 17)
- Graham, Frances K.
  - Letter re Frances and David Graham files., 1986. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Commission (past presidents)., 1976-1977. (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Nominating committee chairman., 1976-1977. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - General., 1976-1977. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Budget / financial., 1973-1976, 1980. (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Award committee., 1973-1975. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Deception committee., 1973-1976. (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Emeritus status., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Ethics committee., 1974. (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Information retrieval committee., 1974. (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Letters, miscellaneous., 1973-1975. (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Local arrangements., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Membership committee., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Michigan corporation report., 1974. (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Nominations committee., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Obrist, Dr. Paul (president-elect)., 1974. (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Program for 1974 Annual Meeting., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - 1974 Publications Board., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Safety committee., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Incoming board., 1974. (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Board meeting (outgoing)., 1974. (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Board memos., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - Committees., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - Incoming board., 1973. (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - Outgoing board, 1973,1972-1974. (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - By-laws., 1972-1974. (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - By-laws committee., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 27)
  - Old ballots., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 28)
  - Publications board., 1973. (Box 20, Folder 29)
  - President--to dues., 1973-1974. (Box 20, Folder 30)
  - Post Society for Psychophysiological Research meeting., 1972-1973. (Box 20, Folder 31)
  - President-elect--re appointments., 1972-1973. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Board., 1963-1972. (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Grings, William W.
  - Lacroix, Michael--correspondence., 1987. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Administration., November 1966-October 1967. (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Administration., October 1967-December 31, 1967. (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Administration., January 1968-March 1968. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Administration., April 1968-November 1968. (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Gustafson, Lawrence A.
  - Active job applicants., 1964-1965. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to--re positions., 1964-1965. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from--re positions., 1964-1965. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Positions filled., 1963-1964. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Change of address., 1964-1965. (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Johnson, Laverne C.
  - New members list and financial statements., 1968-1969. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Official Society for Psychophysiological Research minutes., 1968-1969. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence., 1968-1969. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Lykken, David T.
  - Note to Don Fowles., 1981. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Lykken., 1980-1981. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Society for Psychophysiological Research committees., 1980. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - 1981 meeting plans., 1980-1981. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - AAAS materials., 1979-1981. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - General., 1979-1981,1987. (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Orne, Martin T.--Correspondence up to, December 10, 1963
  - Old Orne--Ax correspondence., 1959-1963. (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Orne correspondence., 1962-1963. (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence., 1962-1963. (Box 13, Folder 21)
- Polygraph Newsletter
  - vol.1 no.1-2., 1955 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Prokasy, William F.
  - General--editorial board., 1980-1983. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - 1982 Annual Meeting., 1981-1982. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - 1983 Annual Meeting., 1982-1983. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Society for Psychophysiology Presidency., 1981-1984. (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Psychophysiological Measurements Newsletter
  - vol.2 no.1-3., 1956 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - vol.3 no.1., 1957 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - vol.4 no.1-3., 1958 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - vol.5 no.1-3., 1959 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - vol.6 no.1-2., 1960 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - vol.7 no.1-2., 1961 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - vol.8 no.1-2., 1962 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - vol. 9., 1963 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Psychophysiology (journal)
  - vol.1 no.1-2., 1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - vol.1 no.3-4; vol.2 no.1-2)., 1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - vol.2 no.3-4; vol.3 no.1-2)., 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - vol.3 no.3-4; vol.4 no.1-2., 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - vol.4 no.3-4; vol.5 no.1-3., 1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - vol.5 no.4-6; vol.6 no.1-3., 1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - vol.6 no.4-6; vol.7 no.1-3., 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - vol.8 no.1., 1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - vol.8 no.2-6., 1971 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - vol.8 no.1-6., 1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - vol.10 no.1-4., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - vol.10 no.5-6., 1973 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - vol.11 no.1-6., 1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - vol.12 no.1-6., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - vol.13 no.1-3., 1976 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - vol.13 no.4-6., 1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - vol.14 no.1-6., 1977 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - vol.15 no.1-4, 6., 1978 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - vol.16 no.1-2, 4., 1979 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - vol.17 no.1-6., 1980 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - vol.18 no.1-3., 1981 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - vol.19 no.2-6., 1982 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - vol.20 no.1-6., 1983 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - vol.21 no.1-5, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Psychophysiology Newsletter
  - vol.1; vol.9., 1955 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Roessler, Robert
  - Miscellaneous papers., 1971-1972. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Minutes., 1971-1972. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence., 1971. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence., 1972. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Stern, John A
  - Programs., 1969-1972, 1974, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence., May 7, 1970-December 5, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1971 meeting at St. Louis., November 1969-December 1971. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Membership rosters., 1970, 1971, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous papers., January 1970-July 1975. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Board meeting minutes and agenda., January 1971-October 1971. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Wenger, Marion A.
  - Letter from Robert Edelberg., 1978. (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Letter from Albert Ax and copies of relevant Newsletters., 1959, 1961, 1971. (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Personal history related to Society for Psychophysiological Research and APA., 1961-1966. (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Archives of Society for Psychophysiological Research president., 1962. (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Early Society for Psychophysiological Research, re Journal., 1962-1965. (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Acceptance of the Society's archives to UCLA., 1977. (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Papers for the journal., 1962. (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Organizational meeting., September 1959. (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Meeting., September 1960. (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Matters for board discussion., 1964. (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - By laws., 1961-1965. (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - re journal., 1964. (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence with Secretary-Treasurer., 1963-1964. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Society for Psychophysiological Research archives., 1971. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Communications to membership., 1963-1964. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with board., 1963-1964. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - General., 1964. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with Albert Ax., 1963-1967. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous., 1964. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Symposium and other correspondence., 1962. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - General correspondence., November 1964-1966. (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Membership roster., 1962. (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Actions of Board of Directors., 1965. (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors meeting., 1966. (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Betty Wieland., 1966. (Box 17, Folder 13)
    General note
    (See also Wieland, Betty, Ph.D)
  - Membership list., October 1976. (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Society for Psychophysiological Research meeting program booklet., 1969. (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Article by Sherwin J. Klein., 1964. (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - re archives of Society for Psychophysiological Research., 1976-1977. (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, re Society for Psychophysiological Research archives., 1976-1977. (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Journal--manuscripts reviewed., 1964-1965. (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Journal--manuscripts reviewed., 1966. (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Abstracts--correspondence., 1964-1965. (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - Abstracts--submitted., 1965. (Box 17, Folder 22)
  - General correspondence., 1966, 1970. (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - Papers submitted for program at 2nd Annual Meeting., 1962. (Box 17, Folder 24)
  - Program for Society for Psychophysiological Research., 1962. (Box 17, Folder 25)
  - Membership., 1964. (Box 17, Folder 26)
  - Journal--manuscripts submitted., 1964-1967. (Box 17, Folder 27)
  - General., 1964-1981. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Notes and letters on the purpose and aims of the Society for Psychophysiological Research., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Letter and copy of Presidential Address from David T. Graham., 1971. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Membership lists., 1964. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Psychophysiological newsletter., vol.2 no.1-2; vol.3 no.1-2; vol.4 no.1-3., 1956-1958 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Psychophysiology newsletter, 1959-1963, vol.5 no.1-3; vol.6 no.1; vol.7 no.4; vol.8 no.3-4; vol.9. (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Venables, Peter H.--presidential correspondence., 1974-1975, 1977. (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Donchin, Emanuel--presidential correspondence., 1979-1980. (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - History of Society for Psychophysiological Research (notes, letters, journals, etc.)., 1959-1971. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography of psychophysiology, psychosomatic medicine, and related concepts., 1963. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - A selected bibliography for psychophysiology., November 1968. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Society for Psychophysiological Research Annual Meeting programs., 1965, 1970, 1975-1977, 1982. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence., September 1977. (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Letters concerning presidential correspondence for archival purposes., 1977-1979. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Mimeograph letters to Society for Psychophysiological Research membership., 1968-1969. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Memos from Dr. Bernard Engel., 1970. (Box 19, Folder 8)
- Wieland, Betty
  - Address changes., 1966-1967. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors., 1965. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors--correspondence., 1967-1968. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Clinton C. Brown., 1965-1966, 1968. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Grings, William W.--correspondence., 1967. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Bryan, Mary Jo., 1965. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Committee reports. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Convention invitations., 1965-1968. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Dykman, Roscoe A., 1965-1967. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Edelberg, Robert., 1965-1967. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Exhibitor's fees., 1965-1967. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Financial (Gustafson)., 1964. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Journal subscriptions., 1965-1967. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - MacGregor Park National Bank., 1965. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Margolin, Sydney G., 1966. (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - 1965 Annual Meeting., November 1965. (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - 1966 Annual Meeting., 1965-1967. (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Resignations., 1965-1968. (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - SDC proposal 438., 1963. (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Special committees., 1966. (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Stern, John., 1965-1967. (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Sternbach, Richard., 1966-1967. (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Subscription lists., 1967. (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Wenger, M.A., 1963-1964, 1966-1967. (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Williams and Wilkins., 1965-1968. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Application forms. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Vitae., 1966-1968. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Rosters., 1967. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Employment., 1966-1967. (Box 12, Folder 5)